<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Section xmlns="urn:com.io7m.structural:8:0"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         id="e7b8d1c0-1329-4bcd-aabb-276d0219593b"
         title="Model">

  <Subsection title="Overview">
    <Paragraph>
      The <Term type="package">cardant</Term> package provides a server-based application to track inventory. It stores
      detailed information about types of <Link target="98e6044d-2cd6-4646-be40-cf57695ee9e7">items</Link>, and can
      store the counts of those items present in defined
      <Link target="d5fa706f-6150-4c71-b5be-311e2680b89a">locations</Link>.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      This section of the documentation describes the internal <Term type="package">cardant</Term> model.
    </Paragraph>
  </Subsection>

  <Subsection title="Items"
              id="98e6044d-2cd6-4646-be40-cf57695ee9e7">
    <Subsection title="Overview">
      <Paragraph>
        An <Term type="term">item</Term> is an object that is tracked by the inventory system. When the
        <Term type="package">cardant</Term>
        package refers to items, it should more accurately be understood to be referring to
        <Term type="term">classes</Term> of items. That is, the inventory system tracks sets of items of a given class
        within <Link target="d5fa706f-6150-4c71-b5be-311e2680b89a">locations</Link>. An item has
        associated <Link target="64b850d6-ee2a-4e44-bc8a-7a04da7530fc">metadata</Link>, an identifier that uniquely
        identifies the item class, zero or more
        <Link target="32d947cf-5f95-4576-b5f7-104a5a3b82f6">types</Link>
        that can constrain the metadata associated with the item, and a <Term type="term">name</Term>.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>

    <Subsection title="Metadata"
                id="64b850d6-ee2a-4e44-bc8a-7a04da7530fc">
      <Paragraph>
        <Term type="term">Metadata</Term>
        is data associated with an item that describes that item. Items can have any number of metadata values, and
        inventory managers can introduce strong requirements on the presence and types of metadata on items through the
        application of <Link target="32d947cf-5f95-4576-b5f7-104a5a3b82f6">types</Link>.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>

    <Subsection title="Types"
                id="32d947cf-5f95-4576-b5f7-104a5a3b82f6">
      <Paragraph>
        A <Term type="term">type</Term> is a label that can be applied to an item that will constrain the
        <Link target="64b850d6-ee2a-4e44-bc8a-7a04da7530fc">metadata</Link>
        associated with that item. A <Term type="term">type</Term> on an item refers to a
        <Term type="term">type declaration</Term>
        created by the inventory manager. A
        <Term type="term">type declaration</Term>
        is essentially a
        <Term type="term">record type</Term>
        in the sense that it defines a set of named metadata values along with their individual
        <Link target="e0f0dda3-ecba-4571-8464-2a0f81ed25c6">scalar types</Link>.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        Types are intended to ensure the integrity and quality of metadata associated with items, and allow for more
        precise searching. For example, inventory managers might define a <Term type="type">voltage_regulator</Term> type
        that is applied to electronics components within the inventory that are voltage regulators. The
        <Term type="type">voltage_regulator</Term>
        type might be declared to require that metadata includes numeric values
        <Term type="type">input_voltage</Term>
        and
        <Term type="type">output_voltage</Term>
        that describe the input and output voltages of the regulator. Any attempt to update an item that has the
        <Term type="type">voltage_regulator</Term>
        type applied without providing values for the
        <Term type="type">input_voltage</Term>
        and <Term type="type">output_voltage</Term> metadata will be rejected with a clear error message.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        As mentioned, types are intended to facilitate more precise searching. It is possible to, for example, search
        for all items in the inventory that have an <Term type="type">output_voltage</Term> metadata value, but this
        does not imply that all the returned items will be voltage regulators. With a well-designed and well-managed
        inventory, one can simply search for all items that have the type
        <Term type="type">voltage_regulator</Term>
        (and then perhaps narrow down the search by asking for only those items that have an
        <Term type="type">output_voltage</Term>
        value equal to <Term type="type">5.0</Term>).
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>

    <Subsection title="Scalar Types"
                id="e0f0dda3-ecba-4571-8464-2a0f81ed25c6">
      <Paragraph>
        A <Term type="term">scalar type</Term> is a named type derived from one of the following <Term type="term">base
        types</Term>:
      </Paragraph>
      <FormalItem title="Metadata Value Types">
        <Table type="genericTable">
          <Columns>
            <Column>Name</Column>
            <Column>Description</Column>
          </Columns>
          <Row>
            <Cell>
              <Term type="type">Integral</Term>
            </Cell>
            <Cell>
              A type used to express integer values.
            </Cell>
          </Row>
          <Row>
            <Cell>
              <Term type="type">Real</Term>
            </Cell>
            <Cell>
              A type used to express real/fractional values.
            </Cell>
          </Row>
          <Row>
            <Cell>
              <Term type="type">Monetary</Term>
            </Cell>
            <Cell>
              A type used to express monetary values. All values include an associated currency unit.
            </Cell>
          </Row>
          <Row>
            <Cell>
              <Term type="type">Time</Term>
            </Cell>
            <Cell>
              A type used to express timestamp values. All values include a time zone value.
            </Cell>
          </Row>
          <Row>
            <Cell>
              <Term type="type">Text</Term>
            </Cell>
            <Cell>
              A type used to express plain string values.
            </Cell>
          </Row>
        </Table>
      </FormalItem>
      <Paragraph>
        Typically, a named scalar type will augment an existing scalar base type with further constraints such as a <Term type="term">
        bound
      </Term> on the range of allowed values. For example, an inventory manager supervising a stock of computer
        keyboards might define a
        <Term type="type">keyboard</Term>
        <Link target="32d947cf-5f95-4576-b5f7-104a5a3b82f6">type</Link>
        with a <Term type="type">keys</Term> field of a scalar type <Term type="type">keyboard.keys</Term>. The
        <Term type="type">keyboard.keys</Term>
        scalar type might be derived from the
        <Term type="type">Integral</Term>
        scalar type with a bound of <Term type="expression">[68, 104]</Term>, expressing that keyboard may have as few
        as <Term type="constant">68</Term> or as many as
        <Term type="constant">104</Term>
        keys.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>

    <Subsection title="Attachments"
                id="31255944-64ca-4b59-b2fd-e5d31aaad374">
      <Paragraph>
        Items can have zero or more <Term type="term">attachments</Term>. An attachment is simply a file associated with
        the item according to a given <Term type="term">relation</Term>. For example, an electronics component might
        have a PDF datasheet associated with it using a
        <Term type="expression">datasheet</Term>
        relation. Relations are entirely user-defined, and it is the responsibility of the inventory manager to use
        sensible and consistent relations.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
  </Subsection>

  <Subsection title="Stock" id="774506e9-7bfc-44a7-9d0c-f2ba9efbfa23">
    <Subsection title="Overview">
      <Paragraph>
        A <Term type="term">stock instance</Term> is an object that associates
        <Link target="98e6044d-2cd6-4646-be40-cf57695ee9e7">items</Link>
        with
        <Link target="d5fa706f-6150-4c71-b5be-311e2680b89a">locations</Link>. A stock instance effectively
        says "this item is present in this location". A stock instance may be a
        <Link target="4f802611-7049-4b3f-b723-d77c43255d47">set instance</Link>
        or a
        <Link target="b2244c01-6445-4cc8-97e2-9e387e4c99e3">serial instance</Link>.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        Stock instances have globally-unique UUID identifier values.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
    <Subsection title="Set Instance" id="4f802611-7049-4b3f-b723-d77c43255d47">
      <Paragraph>
        A <Term type="term">set instance</Term> is a stock instance that describes a set of items that,
        by themselves, do not have any kind of unique identities.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        For example, an inventory manager that is managing
        an inventory that contains rolls of passive electronics components such as
        <LinkExternal target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resistor">resistors</LinkExternal> would use set
        instances to describe sets of resistors in the inventory. The resistors
        themselves do not have serial numbers or any kind of individual identity and therefore there is no reason
        to (or, in fact, any way to) track the individual resistors; only the <Term type="term">count</Term> of
        resistors has any meaning.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        A set instance always has a count ≥ 0. Attempting to remove items from a set instance such that the
        count would become negative is an error.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
    <Subsection title="Serial Instance" id="b2244c01-6445-4cc8-97e2-9e387e4c99e3">
      <Paragraph>
        A <Term type="term">serial instance</Term> is a stock instance that describes a single item that may
        have one or more identities associated with it.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        For example, an inventory manager that is managing an inventory that
        contains musical instruments would use serial instances to identify individual instruments in
        the inventory. Instruments of each type are distinguished from other instruments of the
        same type by way of <Term type="term">serial numbers</Term>. A <Term type="term">serial number</Term>
        in the <Term type="package">cardant</Term> package is an arbitrary string. Serial numbers are unique for a
        given <Link target="98e6044d-2cd6-4646-be40-cf57695ee9e7">item class</Link> but are not assumed be globally
        unique. After all, two manufacturers of completely different products might coincidentally manage to use
        the same serial numbers for their products. Within a single manufacturer's product range, however, serial
        numbers will most assuredly be unique.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        As mentioned, stock instances do have a guaranteed-unique identifier, so this can be used as a system-enforced
        unique identifier for an item if required.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
    <Subsection title="Repositing"
                id="2083cf7c-5550-408c-a12e-d688427d740d">

      <Subsection title="Overview">
        <Paragraph>
          Stock is added to and removed from locations by <Term type="term">repositing</Term>. Intuitively, a
          <Term type="term">reposit</Term>
          operation atomically adds zero or more instances of an item to a location, and removes zero or more items
          from another location in a single step. A reposit operation is either a
          <Link target="764872ee-f8dc-4020-a2dd-644b196a0e72">set</Link> reposit or
          a <Link target="911f1d39-b69a-4e98-ac79-63305762126f">serial</Link> reposit.
        </Paragraph>
      </Subsection>

      <Subsection title="Set Reposit" id="764872ee-f8dc-4020-a2dd-644b196a0e72">
        <Paragraph>
          A <Term type="term">set reposit</Term> is an operation used to move sets of items that do not, themselves,
          have useful individual identities.
        </Paragraph>
      </Subsection>

      <Subsection title="Serial Reposit" id="911f1d39-b69a-4e98-ac79-63305762126f">
        <Paragraph>
          A <Term type="term">serial reposit</Term> is an operation used to move items that have individual identities.
        </Paragraph>
      </Subsection>

      <Subsection title="Definitions And Invariants" id="b8ca9349-2947-4fa9-9434-1198c65fc153">
        <Paragraph>
          Reposit operations are described by the following algebraic datatype:
        </Paragraph>
        <FormalItem title="Reposit" id="dbb0cef2-fc59-4f83-a9c5-2668ddad500d">
          <Verbatim><![CDATA[
type StockReposit =
  | CAStockRepositRemove CAStockInstanceID
  | CAStockRepositSerialIntroduce CAStockInstanceID CAItemID CALocationID CAItemSerial
  | CAStockRepositSerialMove CAStockInstanceID CALocationID
  | CAStockRepositSerialNumberAdd CAStockInstanceID CAItemSerial
  | CAStockRepositSerialNumberRemove CAStockInstanceID CAItemSerial
  | CAStockRepositSetAdd CAStockInstanceID Long
  | CAStockRepositSetIntroduce CAStockInstanceID CAItemID CALocationID Long
  | CAStockRepositSetMove CAStockInstanceID CAStockInstanceID CALocationID Long
  | CAStockRepositSetRemove CAStockInstanceID Long
  ]]></Verbatim>
        </FormalItem>
        <Paragraph>
          A reposit <Term type="expression">(CAStockRepositSerialIntroduce i t l s)</Term> introduces a
          new serial stock instance <Term type="expression">i</Term> of item
          <Term type="expression">t</Term>, placing it in location
          <Term type="expression">l</Term>, and using the initial serial number
          <Term type="expression">s</Term>.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          A reposit <Term type="expression">(CAStockRepositRemove i)</Term> removes the stock instance
          <Term type="expression">i</Term>.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          A reposit <Term type="expression">(CAStockRepositSerialMove i l)</Term> moves an existing
          serial stock instance <Term type="expression">i</Term> from the location it is currently in
          to the new location <Term type="expression">l</Term>.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          A reposit <Term type="expression">(CAStockRepositSerialNumberAdd i s)</Term> adds a new serial
          number <Term type="expression">s</Term> to an existing
          serial stock instance <Term type="expression">i</Term>.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          A reposit <Term type="expression">(CAStockRepositSerialNumberRemove i s)</Term> removes a serial
          number <Term type="expression">s</Term> from an existing
          serial stock instance <Term type="expression">i</Term>.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          A reposit <Term type="expression">(CAStockRepositSetIntroduce i t l c)</Term> introduces a
          new set stock instance <Term type="expression">i</Term> of item
          <Term type="expression">t</Term>, placing it in location
          <Term type="expression">l</Term>, and using the initial count
          <Term type="expression">c</Term>.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          A reposit <Term type="expression">(CAStockRepositSetAdd i c)</Term> adds
          <Term type="expression">c</Term> items to an existing set stock instance <Term type="expression">i</Term>.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          A reposit <Term type="expression">(CAStockRepositSetMove i0 i1 l c)</Term> moves
          <Term type="expression">c</Term> items from an existing set stock instance <Term type="expression">i0</Term>
          to the set stock instance <Term type="expression">i1</Term>.
        </Paragraph>
        <Paragraph>
          A reposit <Term type="expression">(CAStockRepositSetRemove i c)</Term> removes
          <Term type="expression">c</Term> items from an existing set stock instance <Term type="expression">i</Term>.
        </Paragraph>
      </Subsection>
    </Subsection>
  </Subsection>

  <Subsection title="Locations"
              id="d5fa706f-6150-4c71-b5be-311e2680b89a">
    <Subsection title="Overview">
      <Paragraph>
        A <Term type="term">location</Term> is an object that tracks
        <Link target="98e6044d-2cd6-4646-be40-cf57695ee9e7">item counts</Link>. Locations, as a concept, are kept
        deliberately abstract to allow for a wide range of use-cases. A location might represent a physical storage bin
        in a warehouse, or it might represent a deployed computer system that has been built using items taken from the
        inventory. By treating locations as generic containers in this manner, the system is intended to allow for
        supporting different use cases such as managing retail inventory, or managing the deployment of computer parts
        in a laboratory. Locations are <Link target="c4dba23a-9e90-4ac0-b5a5-c0a6f16609a4">hierarchical</Link>.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>

    <Subsection title="Metadata">
      <Paragraph>
        Locations carry <Link target="64b850d6-ee2a-4e44-bc8a-7a04da7530fc">metadata</Link> in the same manner as items.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>

    <Subsection title="Types">
      <Paragraph>
        Locations can have applied <Link target="32d947cf-5f95-4576-b5f7-104a5a3b82f6">types</Link> in the same manner
        as items.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>

    <Subsection title="Attachments">
      <Paragraph>
        Locations can have <Link target="31255944-64ca-4b59-b2fd-e5d31aaad374">attachments</Link> in the same manner as
        items.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>

    <Subsection title="Hierarchy"
                id="c4dba23a-9e90-4ac0-b5a5-c0a6f16609a4">
      <Paragraph>
        Locations form a <Term type="term">hierarchy</Term> (specifically, a tree) in that any location may have any
        number of <Term type="term">child locations</Term>, although a location may only have at most one parent.
        Locations can be <Term type="term">reparented</Term> at any time; they are not locked into having whichever
        parent they had when they were created.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        The hierarchical nature of locations can be used to model different kinds of inventory arrangements. For
        example, a manager of computer laboratories might define <Term type="term">Laboratory A</Term> and
        <Term type="term">Laboratory B</Term>
        locations. Within those locations, the manager might define locations
        <Term type="term">Computer A1</Term>, <Term type="term">Computer A2</Term>,
        <Term type="term">Computer A3</Term>, and so on. Within the <Term type="term">Computer A1</Term> location, the
        manager might place a single motherboard <Link target="98e6044d-2cd6-4646-be40-cf57695ee9e7">item</Link>, one or
        more CPU items, and so on, from the inventory. This allows the manager to know what computer parts they have,
        and the computers in which those parts are being used in the laboratories under their supervision. Additionally,
        should one assembled computer be moved from one laboratory to another, the manager can simply reparent the
        computer location to the new laboratory.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        Conversely, a manager of a retail business might define a <Term type="term">Storage Room A</Term> location, and
        then within that location, define <Term type="term">Shelf A01</Term>,
        <Term type="term">Shelf A02</Term>, <Term type="term">Shelf A03</Term>, etc. The manager can then place items
        onto those storage shelf locations. This allows the manager to track what stock they have, and exactly where
        they're keeping each kind of item.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
  </Subsection>

  <Subsection title="Type Packages" id="0f4b9332-c2d2-4460-9fb5-f2594b854219">
    <Subsection title="Overview">
      <Paragraph>
        <Link target="32d947cf-5f95-4576-b5f7-104a5a3b82f6">Types</Link> are introduced into
        a running <Term type="package">cardant</Term> server using <Term type="term">type packages</Term>.
        A <Term type="term">type package</Term> is simply a named, versioned container of types that can
        be uploaded and installed into the server's database atomically.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
    <Subsection title="Names" id="56df9b58-93ac-4444-b76e-aacacd0e88ce">
      <Paragraph>
        Type packages are identified by their <Term type="term">name</Term> and <Term type="term">version</Term>.
        It is not permitted to have two packages with the same name but different versions installed at the same
        time. A type package name is a
        <LinkExternal target="https://www.io7m.com/software/lanark/">Lanark</LinkExternal> dotted name (such
        as <Term type="expression">com.io7m.example</Term>) and the types declared within the package have their
        names derived by concatenating their unqualified names onto the end of the package name. So, for example,
        a package <Term type="expression">com.io7m.example</Term> that contains a scalar type named
        <Term type="expression">t</Term> will cause the scalar type <Term type="expression">com.io7m.example:t</Term>
        to be created on the server when the package is installed.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
    <Subsection title="Imports">
      <Paragraph>
        A type package may <Term type="term">import</Term> other type packages. An <Term type="term">import</Term>
        consists of a <Link target="56df9b58-93ac-4444-b76e-aacacd0e88ce">package name</Link> and
        a <Term type="term">version range</Term>. When a user tries to install a type package
        <Term type="expression">p</Term>, each import <Term type="expression">i</Term> declared by
        <Term type="expression">p</Term> is examined, and the server inspects its own set of installed
        packages and verifies that a package is installed with both a name that matches <Term type="expression">i</Term>
        and a version that falls within the range declared by <Term type="expression">i</Term>. If no such package
        exists, the type package installation is rejected and the system is left untouched.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        For the sake of simplicity, and because the number of installed type packages is expected to be small
        and not change particularly often, imports are merely an install-time check. It is possible (but heavily
        discouraged) for type packages to refer to types in packages that they have not imported.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
    <Subsection title="Serialization">
      <Paragraph>
        Type packages are serialized using the given
        <Link target="85488da3-174a-43f9-8f93-8d59bfab2846">XML schema</Link>.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
  </Subsection>

  <Subsection title="Security"
              id="bc059ce6-a6c2-42c1-bc20-c84851bd347b">
    <Subsection title="Overview">
      <Paragraph>
        The <Term type="package">cardant</Term> package uses role-based access control for all operations.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
    <Subsection title="Roles"
                id="04998c79-db74-4769-b649-1bac687f9451">
      <Paragraph>
        Each user has a set of
        <Link target="1bb88043-9712-4719-bdb7-829777586149">roles</Link>
        associated with it. When the user attempts to perform an operation on the server, the account's roles are
        checked to see if it has permission to perform the action.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph>
        A role <Term type="variable">R</Term> may be <Term type="term">granted</Term> to a user
        <Term type="variable">A</Term>
        by user <Term type="variable">B</Term> if
        <Term type="variable">B</Term>
        has role <Term type="variable">R</Term>. Accordingly, a role <Term type="variable">R</Term> may be
        <Term type="term">revoked</Term>
        from a user
        <Term type="variable">A</Term>
        by user <Term type="variable">B</Term> if
        <Term type="variable">B</Term>
        has role <Term type="variable">R</Term>.
      </Paragraph>
      <Paragraph id="f57f5739-f60b-4eeb-b31c-99be0efbfde4">
        A user holding the <Term type="expression">inventory.admin</Term> role effectively always has all available
        roles. If new roles are added in future versions of the <Term type="package">cardant</Term> package, users
        holding the <Term type="expression">inventory.admin</Term> role will be automatically granted the new roles. It
        is recommended to limit this role to a single user, and to avoid using that user account for day-to-day
        operations.
      </Paragraph>
    </Subsection>
    <Subsection title="Defined Roles"
                id="1bb88043-9712-4719-bdb7-829777586149">
      <Paragraph>
        The following roles are available:
      </Paragraph>
      <FormalItem title="Roles">
        <xi:include href="m-roles.xml"/>
      </FormalItem>
    </Subsection>
  </Subsection>

  <Subsection title="Audit Log"
              id="021fa938-f249-4620-a938-959b308e1d1f">
    <Paragraph>
      The server maintains an append-only <Term type="term">audit log</Term> consisting of a series of
      <Term type="term">audit events</Term>. An <Term type="term">audit event</Term> has an integer
      <Term type="term">id</Term>, an <Term type="term">owner</Term> (represented by an account UUID),
      a <Term type="term">timestamp</Term>, a <Term type="term">type</Term>, and a
      <Term type="term">message</Term>
      consisting of a set of key/value pairs.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      Each operation that changes the underlying database typically results in an event being logged to the audit log.
    </Paragraph>
  </Subsection>

  <Subsection title="Inventory API"
              id="3dff8219-1792-41a3-bd8b-797efe61348c">
    <Paragraph>
      The <Term type="term">inventory API</Term> is the interface exposed to user clients. It exposes
      a <LinkExternal target="https://www.io7m.com/software/cedarbridge">Cedarbridge</LinkExternal>-based API over HTTP,
      using the included
      <Link target="18b8c54d-2127-4a9f-9321-980ea59a568e">schema</Link>.
    </Paragraph>
    <Paragraph>
      The inventory API is the primary means by which clients perform operations on the server.
    </Paragraph>
  </Subsection>

</Section>